<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="ch_installation">

<title>Downloading, Installing, and Compiling SMOKE</title>

<section>

<title>Introduction</title>

<para>Instructions on how to download and install SMOKE are provided in <xref linkend="sect_install_download" /> and <xref linkend="sect_install_install" />. <xref linkend="sect_install_compile" /> describes how to compile SMOKE for UNIX platforms other than those supported by CMAS. The SMOKE compile scripts are configured to use a UNIX C-shell environment, so they are not useful for creating Windows-based SMOKE files; using SMOKE with any version of the Windows operating system is not supported. If your operating system is one of the types supported by CMAS, you need only to download the SMOKE executables available from the <ulink url="http://www.cmascenter.org/html/models.html">CMAS Model Clearinghouse</ulink>.</para>

</section>

<section id="sect_install_download">

<title>Downloading SMOKE</title>

<para>Steps for downloading SMOKE:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Go to the <ulink url="http://www.cmascenter.org/html/models.html">CMAS Model Clearinghouse</ulink>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Click on the SMOKE link in the list of CMAS-supported products.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If you have already registered with CMAS, enter your email address and password. Otherwise, click the "Register now" link and complete the registration form.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>You will be sent to the CMAS Download Center. Select SMOKE as the product you wish to download and select your computer and compiler type.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Download the installation script (<filename>smoke_install.csh</filename>), the source code, scripts, and executables archive (<filename>smoke_${version}.Linux2_x86_64pg.tar.gz</filename>), and the test case data files (<filename>smoke_${version}.nctox.MOVES.data.tar.gz</filename>). Save these files in the same directory on your machine.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</section>

<section id="sect_install_install">

<title>Installing SMOKE</title>

<para>Steps for installing SMOKE:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Make sure that the three files you downloaded from the CMAS website are in the same directory.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Choose the directory where you want to install SMOKE and the data files. This directory will be known as your <filename class="directory"><envar>SMK_HOME</envar></filename> directory.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>At the command line, type:</para>

<para><userinput><command>setenv</command> <envar>SMK_HOME</envar> <replaceable>&lt;your selected directory for SMOKE installation&gt;</replaceable></userinput></para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis> the SMOKE scripts are designed to run under the UNIX C-shell (either <command>csh</command> or <command>tcsh</command>); the scripts will not work with other shells such as <command>bash</command>.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Make sure your <filename class="directory"><envar>SMK_HOME</envar></filename> directory exists by typing the following command on the command line:</para>

<para><userinput><command>mkdir -p</command> <filename class="directory"><envar>$SMK_HOME</envar></filename></userinput></para>

</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Go to the directory when you have saved the SMOKE installation files.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Type the following at the command line:</para>

<para><userinput><command>source</command> <filename>smoke_install.csh</filename></userinput></para>

<para>This command will unzip and install the SMOKE files in your <filename class="directory"><envar>SMK_HOME</envar></filename> directory. If the script encounters any problems, it will print an error message to point you to the problem.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The <envar>SMK_HOME</envar> setting is needed by the SMOKE scripts. Therefore, it is best to always have this setting defined when you log into your computer. To do this, perform the following additional steps before proceeding:</para>

<orderedlist continuation="continues">
<listitem>
<para>Go to your home directory, then use a text editor to view the <filename>.cshrc</filename> file (note that this file is a hidden file, which can be listed in UNIX using the <command>ls -a</command> command at the prompt).</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In the <filename>.cshrc</filename> file, add the following line:</para>

<para><userinput><command>setenv</command> <envar>SMK_HOME</envar> <replaceable>&lt;your selected directory for SMOKE installation&gt;</replaceable></userinput></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Save and close the <filename>.cshrc</filename> file. Your <filename class="directory"><envar>SMK_HOME</envar></filename> directory will now be defined automatically when you log into the computer or when you open a new <command>xterm</command> window.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Now you are ready to run the SMOKE nctox case. Running SMOKE is described in <xref linkend="ch_scripts" />, which discusses using the SMOKE scripts. Please refer to <xref linkend="sect_scripts_run_example" /> for instructions on running the example scripts for the nctox case. The current SMOKE documentation can be found online at <ulink url="http://www.smoke-model.org" />.</para>

</section>

<section id="sect_install_compile">

<title>Compiling SMOKE for UNIX</title>

<para>If the executables for your platform are not available from the CMAS web site, you will need to compile SMOKE for your system. You may also need to compile SMOKE if you would like to modify the source code. The following steps will help get you set up to compile SMOKE.</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem>
<para>Install SMOKE as described in <xref linkend="sect_install_install" />. </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Download and compile the I/O API library from the <ulink url="https://www.cmascenter.org/ioapi/">I/O API home page</ulink>. The I/O API can be installed in <filename><envar>$SMK_HOME</envar>/subsys/ioapi</filename> </para>
<para>[1] Create symbolic link to the IOAPI source code directory (ioapi) to the <filename><envar>$SMK_HOME</envar>/subsys/ioapi/ioapi/</filename> directory.</para>
<para>[2] Create symbolic link to the IOAPI <filename>libioapi.a</filename> library file and  utility programs (<filename>datshift, jul2greg, greg2jul and so on</filename>) to the <filename><envar>$SMK_HOME</envar>/subsys/ioapi/Linux2_x86_64ifort/</filename> directory.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>After the appropriate libraries and compile options have been installed, you can source an Assigns file to ensure that your system is configured properly.</para>

<para><userinput><command>cd</command> <filename class="directory"><envar>$SMK_HOME</envar>/subsys/smoke/assigns</filename></userinput></para>

<para><userinput><command>source</command> <filename>ASSIGNS.nctox.cmaq.cb05_soa.us12-nc</filename></userinput></para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>You should now be ready to compile the SMOKE programs. Change directories to <filename class="directory"><envar>$SMKOOT</envar>/src/</filename>.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>At the UNIX prompt, type:</para>
<para><userinput><command>make</command></userinput></para>

</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>After running the <filename>Makeall</filename> script, you should check the <envar>$SMK_BIN</envar> directory to check the executables.</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>Once you have compiled the SMOKE programs, you can run the SMOKE example scripts following the instructions in <xref linkend="sect_scripts_run_example" />.</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>

</chapter>
